A Guide to the University of Virginia School of Medicine Student Notebook Collection, 1836-1943
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library
University of Virginia School of Medicine Student Notebook Collection
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library, University of Virginia
MS-37
17 boxes, 5"x10.5"x15.5," 7.2 feet, 121 items
Historical Collections
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The notebooks were donated by various people including Dr. Malcolm Foote Sher, Dr. Porter B. Echols, Jr., the Dr. Armistead P. Booker family, Dr. Weaver, Ms. Roberta Senechal, Jethro Meriwether Hurt, III, Mr. James Skalnik, and James D. Webb. Several notebooks were purchased.
Biographical Information
The student notebooks contain the notes that medical students took in their classes or laboratories at the University of Virginia. Some of the notebooks belonged to men who would become faculty members at UVa. Those include Armistead Page Booker who was Clinical Instructor in Pediatrics in 1947 and retired from his position of Associate Professor in 1985; William Beverly Towles who became an instructor in anatomy in the 1872-73 session and became Professor of Anatomy and Materia Medica, serving in that position until his death in 1893; Charles Bruce Morton who is listed as the Professor of Clinical Surgery and Gynecology in the "University of Virginia Record" for 1944-45 and was last listed in the "University of Virginia School of Medicine Record" for 1969-70; and Oscar Swineford was listed as an instructor in Medicine in the "University of Virginia Record" of March 15, 1928 and was last listed as a Professor of Internal Medicine in the 1966-67 "University of Virginia Record."
Many of the students included the names of their professors and instructors and those include John Staige Davis, James L. Cabell, John P. Emmet, Henry Howard, Socrates Maupin, Albert H. Tuttle, Stephen Hurt Watts, John Henry Neff, William Hall Goodwin, Lawrence T. Royster, Allen F. Voshell, E. Wood, John Campbell Hortenstine, Henry Bearden Mulholland, Edwin Partridge Lehman, William Henry Parker, William Roland Hill, Charles Bruce Morton, William Edward Bray, Kenneth Boyd Grim, Samuel Alexander Vest, Edgar Wilson Kirby, Bruno Barelare, Tiffany Johns Williams, John McIntire Nokes, William Wirt Waddell, McLemore Birdsong, William Gayle Crutchfield, Everett Cato Drash, Edwin Webster Shearburn, Byrd Stuart Leavell, William Maryon Moir, David Cole Wilson, Thomas Shepherd Englar, Byrd Stuart Leavell, Oscar Swineford, Staige Davis Blackford, John Osborne McNeel, James Alexander Waddell, Dudley Crofford Smith, Fletcher Drummond Woodward, Vincent William Archer, George Cooper, Eugene Markley Landis, George McLean Lawson, Claude C. Coleman, Theodore Hough, William Douglas Macon, William Edward Brown, and Leroy Adelbert Calkins.
In our rare book collection there are other items of interest related to the student notebooks. These include the Syllabus of the Lectures on Medical Jurisprudence and on the Treatment of Poisoning and Suspended Animation, Delivered in the University of Virginia, by Robley Dunglison and printed in 1827 as well as volumes related to anatomy by William Beverley Towles. Towles' works are Notes on Anatomy printed in 1886, Anatomy Notes published in 1890, Notes on Anatomy published in 1893, and Descriptive Anatomy published in 1898 and 1904.
Scope and Content
The notebooks range from 1836-1943 and include notes taken in classes for anatomy, surgery, physiology, gynecology, midwifery, chemistry, materia medica, preventive medicine, practice of medicine, ENT, bacteriology, jurisprudence, pharmacy, organic chemistry, pathology, psychobiology, internal medicine, toxicology, clinical diagnosis, histology, biology, syphilology, embryology, heart disease, urology, physical diagnosis, dermatology, pediatrics, orthopedics, Roentgenology, edpidemiology, nervous system, case teaching, and insanity.
Arrangement
The first 13 boxes and Box 14 through folder 5 are arranged chronologically. From Box 14, folder 6 the arrangement is in the order received.
Contents List
- Student notebook: Notes on Midwifery 1840-1841, ADS notebook (Box-folder 001-001)
  The notes were taken at the University of Virginia by Alexander M. Campbell from Dr. Howards' lectures, Session of 1840 and 41. Included are directions for purifying gold, silver solder, gold solder, stannate, flux, and enamels. According to the "Catalogue of the Officers and Students of the University of Virginia," A. M. Campbell, from Amherst, Va., attended UVA in 1840-41 in the schools of Anatomy and Surgery.
  Professor: Henry Howard (Professor of Physiology, Medicine, Obstetrics, and Medical Jurisprudence).
  Textbook: Alfred Velpeau, Translated from the French with notes by Charles D. Meigs. An Elementary Treatise on Midwifery, or, Principles of Tokology and Embryology (Philadelphia: Grigg & Elliot, 1838).
- Student notebook: Lectures of Professors J[ames] L. Cabell, [Henry] Howard, [John S.] Davis and [Socrates] Maupin 1854-1855, ADS notebook (Box-folder 001-002)
  The notes were taken by James Sandford, M.D. from Pattonsburg, Virginia. Accounts related to medical visits are also included. According to the "Catalogue of the Officers and Students of the University of Virginia," James Sandford attended UVA during the 1854-55 session.
  Schools Attended: Chemistry, Medicine, Physiology and Surgery, and Anatomy.
  Professors: James L. Cabell (Professor of Comparative Anatomy, Physiology and Surgery), Henry Howard (Professor of Medicine), John S. Davis (Lecturer on Anatomy, Materia Medica and Therapeutics), and S. Maupin (Professor of Chemistry)
  Textbooks: Professor Cabell: James L. Cabell, Syllabus of Lectures on Comparative Anatomy and Physiology (Charlottesville, University of Virginia: McKennie & Son, 1853); William Benjamin Carpenter, Elements of Physiology: Including Physiological Anatomy (Philadelphia: Blanchard and Lea, 1851); William Senhouse Kirkes, assisted by James Paget, Manual of Physiology (Philadelphia: Lea and Blanchard, 1849); Robert Druitt, The Principles and Practice of Modern Surgery (Philadelphia: Lea and Blanchard, 1853). Professor Howard: Henry Howard, Outlines of Medical Jurisprudence (Charlottesville, Virginia: Noel, 1845); Theodoric Romeyn Beck and John B. Beck, Elements of Medical Jurisprudence (Philadelphia: Thomas, Cowperthwait, 1838) Or Alfred Swaine Taylor, Medical Jurisprudence (Philadelphia: Blanchard and Lea, 1853); Alfred Velpeau, Translated from the French with notes by Charles D. Meigs, A Complete Treatise on Midwifery: or, the Theory and Practice of Tokology: including Diseases of Pregnancy, Labor, and the Puerperal State (Philadelphia: Lindsay and Blakiston, 1852); George B. Wood, A Treatise on the Practice of Medicine (Philadelphia: Lippincott, Grambo, and Co., 1855). Professor Davis: Erasmus Wilson (edited by Paul B. Goddard), A System of Human Anatomy, General and Special (Philadelphia: Blanchard and Lea, 1852); Robley Dunglison, General Therapeutics and Materia Medica: Adapted for a Medical Text-book (Philadelphia: Blanchard and Lea, 1853).Professor Maupin: George Fownes, Rudimentary Chemistry for the Use of Beginners (London: 1854); Edward Turner, Elements of Chemistry: including the History of the Imponderables and the Inorganic Chemistry (Philadelphia: Thomas, Cowperthwait & Co., 1846) for reference; Edward Graham, Elements of Inorganic Chemistry: including the Applications of the Science in the Arts (Philadelphia: Blanchard and Lea, 1858) for reference; Victor Regnault, Elements of Chemistry: for the Use of Colleges, Academies, and Schools (translated from the French by T. Forrest Betton, and edited with notes by James C. Booth and William L. Faber) (Philadelphia: J. B. Lippincott, 1856) for reference; Frederick A. Abel and C. L. Bloxam, Handbook of Chemistry, Theoretical, Practical and Technical (London: J. Churchill, 1854) for reference.
- Syllabuses on Chemistry by Dr. J. A. Templeton, M.D. 1854-1855, ADS notebook (Box-folder 001-003)
  According to the "Catalogue of the Officers and Students of the University of Virginia," James A. Templeton from Augusta, Virginia, attended UVA during the 1854-55 session.
  Professor: S. Maupin (Professor of Chemistry)
  Textbooks: George Fownes, Rudimentary Chemistry for the Use of Beginners (London: 1854); Edward Turner, Elements of Chemistry: including the History of the Imponderables and the Inorganic Chemistry (Philadelphia: Thomas, Cowperthwait & Co., 1846) for reference; Edward Graham, Elements of Inorganic Chemistry: including the Applications of the Science in the Arts (Philadelphia: Blanchard and Lea, 1858) for reference; Victor Regnault, Elements of Chemistry: for the Use of Colleges, Academies, and Schools (translated from the French by T. Forrest Betton, and edited with notes by James C. Booth and William L. Faber) (Philadelphia: J. B. Lippincott, 1856) for reference; Frederick A. Abel and C. L. Bloxam, Handbook of Chemistry, Theoretical, Practical and Technical (London: J. Churchill, 1854) for reference.
- Student notebook: Surgery 1855-1856, ADS notebook with drawings (Box-folder 001-004)
  The notes were taken by William Joseph Jones, a resident of Amherst County, Virginia, born in Fluvanna County, Virginia. Jones, has made drawings of Jno. S. Davis, Jas. L. Cabell, Henry Howard, and S[ocrates] Maupin.
  Professor: James L. Cabell (Professor of Physiology and Surgery).
  Textbooks: John C. Dalton, Jr., A Treatise on Human Physiology; Designed for the Use of Students and Practitioners of Medicine (Philadelphia: Blanchard and Lea, 1859); Druitt, The Principles and Practice of Modern Surgery (Philadelphia: Lea and Blanchard, 1853).
- Student notebook: Physiology lectures by Dr. J[ames] L. Cabbell [Cabell] 1867 November 14 - 1868 April 16, ADS notebook (Box-folder 001-005)
  The notes were taken by William B. Towles from Cumberland, Virginia. According to the "Catalogue of the University of Virginia, 1868-69," William Beverly Towles received his MD degree in 1869. Dr. Towles, was a distinguished anatomist. He entered the University of Virginia as a student of medicine in 1867. In 1872 he was elected Demonstrator of Anatomy, and, upon the death of Dr. John Staige Davis in 1885, succeeded him as Professor of Anatomy. He worked for the University of Virginia until he died on September 15, 1893.
  Schools Attended: Chemistry and Pharmacy, Medicine, Physiology and Surgery, and Anatomy and Materia Medica.
  Textbook: John C. Dalton, Jr., A Treatise on Human Physiology; Designed for the Use of Students and Practitioners of Medicine (Philadelphia: Blanchard and Lea, 1867).
- Student notebook: University of Virginia Materia Medica lectures by Dr. [John Staige] Davis 1868-1869, ADS notebook (Box-folder 001-006)
  The notes were taken by A. M. Hill from Bastrop, Texas. Hill lists a roll of the medical class at UVa for the 1868-69 session, including Walter Reed. Hill has 44 names written down with an additional 3 who took only one medical course. According to the "Catalogue of the University of Virginia, 1968-69," Augustus Middleton Hill was a student during the 1968-69 session.
  Professor: John Staige Davis (Professor of Anatomy, Materia Medica and Botany).
  Textbook: George B. Wood, A Treatise on Therapeutics, and Pharmacology, or Materia Medica (Philadelphia, J.B. Lippincott & Co., 1868).
- Student notebook: Notes on the Practice of Medicine by T. B. Pugh, Session 1873-74, University of Virginia 1873-1874, ADS notebook (Box-folder 001-007)
  The notes were taken at the University of Virginia by T. B. Pugh from Napoleonville, Louisiana, Woodlawn Plantation. According to the "Catalogue of the Officers and Students of the University of Virginia," Thomas Bryan Pugh was a student during the 1973-74 session.
  Schools Attended: Chemistry (General and Industrial) and Pharmacy, Medicine, Physiology and Surgery, and Anatomy and Materia Medica.
  Professor: James F. Harrison (Professor of Medical Jurisprudence, Obstetrics and Practice of Medicine)
  Textbooks: Austin Flint, A Treatise on the Principles and Practice of Medicine; Designed for the Use of Practitioners and Students of Medicine (Philadelphia: H. C. Lea, 1873); Henry Hartshorne, Essentials of the Principles and Practice of Medicine: a Handbook for Students and Practitioners (Philadelphia: Henry C. Lea, 1874).
- Student notebook: Lectures on Physiology and Surgery by Professor Cabell. 1873 October - 1874 January 15, ADS notebook bound with copied lecture notes. (Box-folder 001-008)
  The notes were taken by T. B. Pugh. For more information on Pugh see Box-folder 001-007.
  Professor: James L. Cabell (Professor of Comparative Anatomy, Physiology and Surgery)
  Textbooks: John C. Dalton, Jr., A Treatise on Human Physiology; Designed for the Use of Students and Practitioners of Medicine (Philadelphia: Blanchard and Lea, 1871); Thomas Henry Huxley, "The Elements of Physiology," The Galaxy (Volume 5, Issue 5, May 1868), 656-657; John Z. Laurence assisted by Robert C. Moon, A Handy-Book of Ophthalmic Surgery for the Use of Practitioners (Philadelphia: Henry C. Lea, 1869); John Ashurst, The Principles and Practice of Surgery (Philadelphia, H.C. Lea, 1871).
- Student notebook: Lectures on Materia Medica, Volume I 1873 October 1 - 1874, ADS notebook (Box-folder 002-001)
  Professor: John Staige Davis (Professor of Anatomy and Materia Medica)
  Textbooks: Erasmus Wilson (edited by Paul B. Goddard), A System of Human Anatomy, General and Special (Philadelphia: Blanchard and Lea, 1868); George B. Wood, A Treatise on Therapeutics, and Pharmacology, or Materia Medica (Philadelphia, J.B. Lippincott & Co., 1868).
- Student notebook: Chemistry Lectures of Thomas Bryan Pugh 1873 October 3 - 1874, ADS notebook bound with copied lecture notes. (Box-folder 002-002)
  Professor: J. W. Mallet (Professor of Chemistry and Pharmacy)
  Textbook: George Fownes, A Manual of Elementary Chemistry, Theoretical and Practical (Philadelphia, H.C. Lea, 1869)
- Student notebook: Lectures on Jurisprudence and Obstetrics by Prof [James F.] Harrison 1873-1874, ADS notebook and unbound pages (Box-folder 002-003)
  The notes were taken by T. B. Pugh. For more information on Pugh see Box-folder 001-007. The unbound pages contain exercises in English and Greek.
  Textbooks: Alfred Swaine Taylor, A Manual of Medical Jurisprudence: with Notes and References to American Decisions by Clement B. Penrose (Philadelphia: Henry C. Lea, 1866); William Leishman, A System of Midwifery, Including the Diseases of Pregnancy and the Puerperal State (Philadelphia, H. C. Lea, 1875).
- Student notebook: Lectures on Pharmacy 1873-1874, ADS notebook (Box-folder 002-004)
  Textbook: Edward Parrish, An Introduction to Practical Pharmacy: Designed as a Text-book for the Student, and as a Guide to the Physician and Pharmaceutist (Philadelphia, Blanchard and Lea, 1856).
- Student notebook: Lectures on Organic Chemistry 1873-1874, ADS notebook bound with copied lecture notes. (Box-folder 002-005)
  Professor: J. W. Mallet (Professor of Chemistry and Pharmacy).
- Student notebook: Materia Medica 1883 October 5 - 1884 April 18, ADS notebook (Box-folder 002-006)
  The notes were taken by O. Nalle. According to the "Catalogue of the Officers and Students of the University of Virginia," Orville Nalle, from Culpeper, Virginia, graduated with an MD degree in 1884.
  Schools Attended: Chemistry, Anatomy, Physiology and Surgery, and Medicine
  Textbooks: Erasmus Wilson (edited by Paul B. Goddard), A System of Human Anatomy, General and Special (Philadelphia: Blanchard and Lea, 1868) Or Henry Gray, Anatomy, Descriptive and Surgical (Philadelphia, H.C. Lea's Son & Co., 1883); Robert Farquharson, A Guide to Therapeutics and Materia Medica (Philadelphia: Henry C. Lea's Son, 1882) Or William Biddle, The Therapeutics of Gynecology and Obstetrics, Comprising the Medical, Dietetic, and Hygienic Treatment of Diseases of Women (Philadelphia, Brinton, 1881) Or Roberts Bartholow, A Practical Treatise on Materia Medica and Therapeutics (New York: Appleton, 1879).
- Student notebook: Notes on Surgery and Material Medica, Book No. 2 1884 February 18 - 1884 May 30 and 1885 January 13, ADS notebook and 16 unbound pages (Box-folder 002-007)
  The notes were taken by O. Nalle. For more information on Nalle see Box-folder 002-006. The surgery lectures were given by Professor [James L.] Cabell. The unbound pages contain information about nerves.
  Professor: James L. Cabell (Professor of Physiology and Surgery)
  Textbooks: John Call Dalton, A Treatise on Human Physiology (Philadelphia: H. C. Lea's Son & Co., 1882) Or Gerald F. Yeo, A Manual of Physiology: A Text-book for Students of Medicine (Philadelphia: Blakiston, 1883); George Wilson, A Handbook of Hygiene and Sanitary Science (Philadelphia, P. Blakiston, son & co., 1884); Horace Green, "Pathology and Treatment of Croup," The United States Democratic Review, vol. 23, issue 125 (Nov 1848); John Ashurst, The Principles and Practice of Surgery (Philadelphia, H.C. Lea, 1882); Thomas Edward Satterthwaite, A Manual of Histology (New York, Wood, 1882) Or Edward E. Klein, Elements of Histology (Philadelphia: Lea Brothers, 1898); A. L. Ranney, A Practical Treatise on Surgical Diagnosis (New York: Wood, 1884).
- Student notebook: Obstetrics, etc. 1889 October 24 - 1890 February 1, ADS notebook (Box-folder 003-001)
  The notes were taken by R. E. Dixon. According to the "Catalogue of the Officers and Students of the University of Virginia," R. Edmond Dixon, from Bristol, Tennessee, attended the 1889-90 and 1890-91 sessions and had an A.B. from King College, Tennessee.
  Schools Attended: Chemistry (General and Industrial), Anatomy and Materia Medica, Physiology and Surgery, and Medicine
  Professor: William C. Dabney (Professor of Obstetrics and Practice of Medicine)
  Textbooks: William S. Playfair, A Treatise on the Science and Practice of Midwifery (Philadelphia: Lea Brothers & Co., 1893); Arthur H. N. Lewers, A Practical Textbook of the Diseases of Women (Philadelphia: P. Blakiston Son & Co., 1890).
- Student notebook: Practice of Medicine (Part I, volume I) 1890 February 4-April 10, ADS notebook (Box-folder 003-002)
  The notes were taken by R. E. Dixon. For more information about Dixon see Box-folder 003-001.
  Textbooks: Adolf von Strumpell, A Text-book of Medicine for Students and Practitioners (New York: D. Appleton and Company, 1887); R. C. M. Page, A Handbook of Physical Diagnosis: of Diseases of the Organs of Respiration and Heart, and of Aortic Aneurism (New York: Vail, 1889).
- Student notebook: Practice of Medicine (Part I, volume II) 1890 April 11-29, AD notebook (Box-folder 003-003)
- Student notebook: Practice of Medicine (Part I, volume III) 1890 April 29-May 8, AD notebook (Box-folder 003-004)
  The notes were taken by [R. E. Dixon].For more information about Dixon see Box-folder 003-001.
- Student notebook: Practice of Medicine (Part II, volume I) 1891 February 3-April 4, ADS notebook (Box-folder 003-005)
  The notes were taken by R. E. Dixon.For more information about Dixon see Box-folder 003-001.
- Student notebook: Practice of Medicine (Part II, volume II) 1891 April 16-June 11, ADS notebook (Box-folder 003-006)
- Student notebook: Materia Medica, Number I 1891 January 2-May 5, ADS notebook (Box-folder 004-001)
  Professor: William B. Towles (Professor of Anatomy and Materia Medica)
  Textbooks: J. Mitchell Bruce, Materia Medica and Therapeutics: An Introduction to the Rational Treatment of Disease (Philadelphia: Lea Bros, 1891).
- Student notebook: Materia Medica, Number II 1891 May 15-June 9, ADS notebook (Box-folder 004-002)
- Student notebook: Materia Medica, [Number III] 1891 June 9-19, ADS notebook (Box-folder 004-003)
- Student notebook: Pathology 1890 December 18-1891 March 11, AD notebook (Box-folder 004-004)
  The notes were taken by [R. E. Dixon]. For more information about Dixon see Box-folder 003-001.
  Textbook: Horace Green, "Pathology and Treatment of Croup," The United States Democratic Review, vol. 23, issue 125 (Nov 1848).
- Student notebook: Surgery, [Volume I] 1891 April 4-22, AD notebook (Box-folder 004-005)
  Professor: Paul B. Barringer (Professor of Physiology and Surgery)
  Textbooks: John B. Roberts, A Manual of Modern Surgery: An Exposition of the Accepted Doctrines and Approved Operative Procedures of the Present Time (Philadelphia, Lea brothers & co., 1890); Ernst Ziegler, A Text-book of Pathological Anatomy and Pathogenesis Translated and Edited for English Students by Donald MacAlister (New York: Wood, 1883-1887); Nicholas Senn, Principles of Surgery (Philadelphia: F. A. Davis, 1891).
- Student notebook: Surgery, [Volume II] 1891 April 22-May 7, AD notebook (Box-folder 004-006)
- Student notebook: Surgery, [Volume III] 1891 May 9-25, AD notebook (Box-folder 004-007)
- Student notebook: Surgery, Volume IV 1891 May 27-June 10, ADS notebook (Box-folder 004-008)
- Student notebook: Surgery, Volume VI 1891 June 22-23, ADS notebook (Box-folder 004-009`)
- Student notebook: Histology 1892 September 19-December 5, ADS notebook with drawings, some in color, also bound with copied lecture notes. (Box-folder 005-001)
  The notes were taken by W. Levi Old from Bennett's Creek, Virginia. He had a B.A. from Randolph-Macon College, Virginia. He was a physician and surgeon in London Bridge, Virginia. He served in the Spanish-American War as a major in the Virginia Volunteer Unit Medical Corps. He was a charter member of the American College of Surgeons, and he worked for many years at St. Vincent's Hospital in Norfolk.
  Schools Attended: Physiology and Surgery, Anatomy and Materia Medica, Practice of Medicine, Chemistry, and Biology and Agriculture
  Professor: Albert H. Tuttle (Professor of Biology)
  Textbook: Edward E. Klein, Elements of Histology (Philadelphia: Lea Brothers, 1898).
- Student notebook: Biology B, Botany, Volume I 1916 September 25-1917 May 16, ADS notebook with drawings, some in color, also bound with copied lecture notes. (Box-folder 005-002)
  The notes were taken by Charles Bruce Morton. According to the "University of Virginia Record Catalogue," Charles Bruce Morton received his MD degree on June 13, 1922. He also received the B.S. degree from the University of Virginia in 1920. In 1927 Dr. Morton was appointed Assistant Professor of Surgery and Gynecology at the University of Virginia School of Medicine and promoted to full professorship in 1936. During the academic year 1953-54, he served as Acting Chairman of the Department of Surgery. He received the University of Virginia's first award of the John Horsley Memorial Prize for Research in Surgery in 1927 and the President and Board of Visitors Sigma Xi Research Prize in 1928. Dr. Morton was a member of the Executive Committee of the University of Virginia Hospital from 1935 to 1954. He has been an Attending Surgeon and Gynecologist at the University of Virginia Hospital, and an Attending Surgeon on the courtesy staff of Martha Jefferson Hospital, 1927.
  In addition to his teaching and surgical practice, Dr. Morton has been active in a number of professional organizations, in which he has held important posts, and he has contributed over seventy articles to medical and surgical publications. His society membership include: International Society of Surgery, American Surgical Association, American College of Surgeons, American Medical Association, Southern Surgical Association (Vice President, 1946), Southeastern Surgical Congress, Eastern Surgical Society (President, 1957), Southern Society of Clinical Surgeons (President, 1946), Virginia Surgical Society (President, 1955), and Medical Society of Virginia.